Finding Aid for George E. Butterfield papers, circa 1902-1969
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George E. Butterfield papers circa 1902-1969
Butterfield, George Ernest, 1883-
1.5 linear foot
88121 Aa 2
Prohibitionist from Bay City, Michigan, dean of Bay City Junior College. Correspondence, 1930-1940; memoranda of various prohibition organizations, 1927-1941; materials relating to revision of the constitution of the Central Association of Congregational Churches of Michigan; other materials concern the Bay City Council of Churches, Crystal Falls, Michigan, and the Michigan Association of Junior Colleges; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Judge Ira W. Butterfield (donor no. 5169 ).
The collection is open to research.
George E. Butterfield was born December 28, 1883 in Bay City, Michigan. Educated at the University of Michigan, he was a teacher, principal, long-time president of the Bay County Historical Society, member of the committee that organized the Bay County Council of Churches, and active in various prohibition organizations. In addition, Butterfield was member of the Bay County Board of Supervisors (1950-1959) and active in his church, the Bay City Congregational Church. He died May 19, 1975.
The Butterfield papers include correspondence, 1930-1940; memoranda of various prohibition organizations, 1927-1941 and materials relating to revision of the constitution of the Central Association of Congregational Churches of Michigan. Other materials concern the Bay City Council of Churches, Crystal Falls, Michigan, and the Michigan Association of Junior Colleges; and photographs.
The papers have been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Prohibition Organizations; Clippings and published material; Topical Files: Other organizational activities and historical interests; and Other Materials.
Subjects:
Allied Citizens for Prohibition.; American Businessmen's Prohibition Foundation.; American Businessmen's Research Foundation.; Bay City (Mich.); Bay City Council of Churches (Mich.); Bay County (Mich.); Butterfield, George Ernest, 1883-; Central Association of Congregational Christian Churches (Mich.); Congregational churches--Michigan--Bay City.; Crystal Falls (Mich.); First Congregational Church (Bay City, Mich.); Intercollegiate Prohibition Association.; Michigan Association of Junior Colleges.; Prohibition--United States.; Prohibition Amendment Advocates.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Butterfield, George Ernest, 1883-; Courthouses.; Crystal Falls (Mich.); Railroad accidents.; Skiing.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Winter.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence 1902-1940
  - 1902-1911 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1940 (Box 1)
- Prohibition Organizations 1927-1941
  - Allied Campaigners for Prohibition 1931 (Box 1)
  - Allied Citizens for Prohibition 1931-1933
    - Educational Committee 1932 (Box 1)
    - Enforcement Committee 1932 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee (Box 1)
    - Finance Committee 1932 (Box 1)
    - Legislative Committee 1931-1932 (Box 1)
    - Meetings 1931-1932 (Box 1)
    - Publicity Committee 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - Allied Forces for Prohibition 1932-1940
    - Board of Strategy 1937-1940 (Box 1)
    - National Committee 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - American Businessmen's Prohibition Foundation 1931-1934 (Box 1)
  - American Businessmen's Research Foundation 1934-1940, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Anti-Saloon League of America 1932-1941 (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate Association for the Study of Alcohol Problems 1939 (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate Prohibition Association 1927-1932 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Anti-Saloon League 1933 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Christian Endeavor Union 1932 (Box 1)
  - Prohibition Amendment Advocates 1931-1934
    - Correspondence and memoranda 1931 (Box 1)
    - Minute book 1931-1934 (Box 1)
  - Prohibition Press Bureau 1932 (Box 1)
  - Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform (Box 1)
- Clippings and published material
  - Clippings 1919-1940 (Box 1)
  - Printed Material, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Topical Files: Other organizational activities and historical interests
  - Bay City Council of Churches
    - Annual Reports 1951-1953 (Box 2)
    - Child Welfare Committee 1951-1953 (Box 2)
    - Findings Committee on Public Forum Concerning Post-War Problems 1943 (Box 2)
    - Minute Book 1949-1962, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1942-1969 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Bay County
    - History (Box 2)
    - Schools
      - General 1903-1922 (Box 2)
      - Portsmouth No. 5 1906-1908 (Box 2)
  - Church Activities
    - Bay County Federation of Churches 1938-1940 (Box 2)
    - Central Association of Congregational Christian Churches (Box 2)
    - Central Association constitution (Box 2)
    - Central Association of Congregational Christian Churches of Michigan (Box 2)
    - General Council meetings (Box 2)
  - Crystal Falls
    - Correspondence (mostly public schools) 1903-1917, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Photographs (mostly postcards), 1908-1911 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Association of Junior Colleges 1928-1967 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Commission on College Accreditation 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Photographs (University of Michigan Class of 1908 (Box 2)
  - Student Notes (University of Michigan)
    - History 89s (Crane) June 1924 (Box 2)
    - Landscape Design ls (Tealdi) June 1924 (Box 2)